At its core, AI is about building software applications
that, at least in some aspects, mimic human behaviors
and capabilities.
So let's start with that most human of activities,
having a chat.
Here's a chat application that I can use to find information
about the history of computing, such as, who was Ada
Lovelace?
And I get a comprehensive and relevant response.
Okay, let's continue the conversation and find out
more about her work with Charles Babbage.
And the model understands the context of a follow-up
prompt and responds with more information.
So, how does generative AI work?
Let's take a closer look.
We start by collecting a large volume of text; which
we'll break down into individual text tokens and use
to train a large language model.
The model encapsulates the semantic relationships
between the tokens.
So it can predict likely sequences of text; for example
to respond to a message in a chat app.
Users engage with the model through the chat app by
submitting prompts: natural language statements or
questions.
And the model responds by generating a sequence of
tokens to complete the conversational dialog.
Generative AI solutions like this enable us to build
intelligent AI agents that can conduct conversations
and even perform actions on our behalf.
An agent, is an AI application that can operate autonomously
by using three key things.
First, a large language model, which acts as the agent's
brain; enabling it to understand language and reason
about how to respond to user requests or environmental
conditions.
Second, an agent has instructions to scope its behavior
and responsibilities.
Think of this as the agent's job description.
And finally, most agents have tools; which enable
them to access the information they need, or use external
systems to perform tasks.
Users can engage with agents through prompts, for
example to get help with finding a particular product.
The agent can use its tools to perform tasks like
searching the web, and placing an order for the required
item.
And finally, report back to the user.
In the computing history application, I can see the
agent settings, including a model, instructions, and
a tool that enables it to search the web.
So I can task the agent with sourcing some parts that
I need for a PC restoration project, and it will search
for what I need on the web.
And now that the agent has done the legwork for me,
I can go ahead and buy the part I need - sweet!
Generative AI apps and agents are at the heart of
modern AI solutions and are driving the development
of amazing new AI-powered capabilities.